<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1123 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1123.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7686 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7686.xml">
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-muffett-tls-ssconion-00" category="info">


  <front>
    <title abbrev="I-D">Self-Signed TLS Certificates for Onion Services</title>

    <author initials="A." surname="Muffett" fullname="Alec Muffett">
      <organization>Open Rights Group</organization>
      <address>
        
        
        <email>alec.muffett@gmail.com</email>
        
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2018" month="January" day="18"/>

    
    
    

    <abstract>


<t>A proposal for standardization of self-signed TLS certificates for use
with “.onion” names as-defined in <xref target="RFC7686"/>, for onion services.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

<t>In this document, the key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”,
“SHALL”, “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”, “SHOULD NOT”, “RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”,
and “OPTIONAL” are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, RFC 2119
<xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

<t>In this document, “.onion name” is to be interpreted as described in
section 1 of <xref target="RFC7686"/>.</t>

<t>In this document “base .onion name” is interpreted to mean the
lowercase canonical representation of a valid .onion name, shorn of
any/all subdomain labels and of the “.onion” label; for example the
base .onion name of “www.foo.facebookcorewwwi.onion” is
“facebookcorewwwi”.</t>

<t>In this document “wildcard .onion name” is interpreted to mean a name
which comprises three or more labels, where:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>the leftmost label is wholly an asterisk (“*”)</t>
  <t>the rightmost label is “onion”</t>
  <t>the second-to-rightmost label is a “base .onion name”</t>
  <t>if the asterisk comprising the leftmost label were replaced with the
single character “A”, the resulting whole would conform with DNS
name syntax as defined in Section 3.5 of <xref target="RFC1034"/> and Section 2.1
of <xref target="RFC1123"/>.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="self-signed-tls-certificates-for-onion-services" title="Self-Signed TLS Certificates for Onion Services">

<section anchor="rationale" title="Rationale">

<t>Tor .onion names are self-asserted cryptographic identifiers which
enable one form of communication on the Tor network.</t>

<t>Possession of the private key for a given .onion name provides defacto
“domain ownership” of that .onion name, and also the ability to
communicate on the Tor network as that .onion name.</t>

<t>Given the self-asserted (and even sometimes ephemeral) nature of
.onion names, combined with the proliferation of protocols which
mandate HTTPS, the requirement for involvement of a Certificate
Authority to issue TLS certificates for a .onion name is a burden.</t>

<t>Therefore: we propose a standard for Self-Signed TLS Certificates for
Onion Services, which Tor-enabled clients may optionally honour as
being as being equally trustworthy to a CA-supplied DV certificate.</t>

<t>This proposal does not replace certification of a .onion name as
currently, or in future, provided under CABForum BRs; in face we call
for extension of CABForum BRs to include DV certificates for “Next
Generation” Onion addresses.</t>

<t>Instead: this standard provides an additional specification to offer
ad-hoc HTTPS capability to enabled clients in limited circumstances.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="certificate-fields" title="Certificate Fields">

<t>All fields that are described in this section MUST be present for a
“Self-Signed TLS Certificate for Onion Services” to be valid.</t>

<t>All fields which are not described in this section MUST NOT exist in
such a certificate.</t>

<section anchor="signature-algorithm" title="Signature Algorithm">

<t>The signature algorithm must conform with <xref target="RFC5280"/> section 4.1.1.2</t>

<section anchor="signature-algorithm-considerations" title="Signature Algorithm Considerations">

<t>Tor implements perfect forward security at the transport layer; in the
spirit of this, and given the narrow and legacy-free nature of clients
which will implement this standard, it would appear retrogressive to
implement anything that does not also meet that functionality.</t>

<t>Therefore we propose that all certificates under this standard SHOULD
be signed with ECDSA.  TODO: Can we tighten this up to kill sucky
algorithms?</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="signature-value" title="Signature Value">

<t>The Signature Value field MUST conform with <xref target="RFC5280"/> section 4.1.1.3</t>

</section>
<section anchor="version" title="Version">

<t>The version field MUST conform with <xref target="RFC5280"/> section 4.1.2.1</t>

</section>
<section anchor="serial-number" title="Serial Number">

<t>The Serial Number MUST conform with <xref target="RFC5280"/> section 4.1.2.2</t>

<t>From section 4.1.2.2, “The serial number MUST be a positive integer
… It MUST be unique for each certificate … MUST NOT use
serialNumber values longer than 20 octets”</t>

<t>In the spirit of that specification, we propose that the serial number
be constructed as the hex digest of:</t>

<t>Digest ( BaseOnionName NotBefore NotAfter )</t>

<t>…where the following applies:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>Digest is MD5</t>
  <t>BaseOnionName is the “base .onion name” (qv) of the Subject
CommonName</t>
  <t>NotBefore and NotAfter are from the certificate Validity and are
represented in ASCII GeneralizedTime Zulu</t>
</list></t>

<t>Thus a serial number for a certificate valid from midnight 1 January
2018 UTC to 13:14:15 on 30 June 2019 UTC for
“www.facebookcorewwwi.onion” would be:</t>

<t>md5(“facebookcorewwwi20180101000000Z20190630131415Z”)</t>

<t>= A8:E2:59:98:F0:2B:E1:40:F6:D2:18:29:8B:68:BB:EA</t>

<section anchor="serial-number-considerations" title="Serial Number Considerations">

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>should we roll the public key into the digest, somehow?</t>
  <t>should we digest with 20-octet-truncated SHA256 instead?</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="issuer" title="Issuer">

<t>The CommonName for the Issuer MUST be the 29-character ASCII string:
“Self-Signed Onion Certificate”.</t>

<t>Other Issuer fields MUST conform with <xref target="RFC5280"/> section 4.1.2.4
conforming to CA/B-Forum BRs for DV Certificates.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="validity" title="Validity">

<t>The certificate validity MUST conform with <xref target="RFC5280"/> section 4.1.2.5</t>

</section>
<section anchor="subject" title="Subject">

<t>The CommonName for the Subject MUST be identical to the first DNS Name
from the list of Subject Alternative Names.</t>

<t>All other Subject fields MUST conform with <xref target="RFC5280"/> section
4.1.2.6, and MUST also conform with extant CA/B-Forum BRs for DV
Certificate Subjects.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="subject-public-key-info" title="Subject Public Key Info">

<t>The Subject Public Key MUST conform with <xref target="RFC5280"/> section 4.2.1.7</t>

<section anchor="subject-public-key-info-considerations" title="Subject Public Key Info Considerations">

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>Per discussion for Signature Algorithm above, it is RECOMMENDED that
the Subject Public Key Algorithm should be “Elliptic Curve Public
Key” of length 256.</t>
  <t>TODO: It would be nice to tighten this up a bit.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="extensions" title="Extensions">

<t>The Extensions MUST contain a Subject Alternative Name extension.</t>

<t>All other Extensions MUST be excluded.</t>

<section anchor="subject-alternative-names" title="Subject Alternative Names">

<t>Requirements:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>The Subject Alternative Names MUST only contain “DNS names”.</t>
  <t>At least one “DNS name” MUST be given.</t>
  <t>The given “DNS names” MAY be “.onion names”.</t>
  <t>The given “DNS names” MAY be “wildcard .onion names”</t>
  <t>The given “DNS names” MUST NOT be other than a “.onion name” or “wildcard .onion name”.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="subject-alternative-names-considerations" title="Subject Alternative Names Considerations">

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>Should we set a maximum number?</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<section anchor="transitive-trust" title="Transitive Trust">

<t>General-purpose HTTP/HTTPS is being extended such that a existing
browser connection to “www.foo.com” will be reused for requests to
“www.bar.com” in the instance that “www.bar.com” matches a Subject
Alternative Name that was provided by the TLS certificate which
authenticated “www.foo.com”.</t>

<t>This arrangement, under a realm of self-signed certificates, would
present an obvious security risk of violation of trust roots in Onion
networking.</t>

<t>Therefore, for the avoidance of this and other similar future security
issues:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>A valid Self-Signed TLS Certificate for Onion Services MUST only
cite a solitary “base .onion name” amongst the Subject Alternative
Names that it lists.</t>
  <t>Clients which support Self-Signed TLS Certificates for Onion
Services MUST NOT trust certificates that cite more than one “base
.onion name”.</t>
</list></t>

<t>TODO: if this risk is mitigated elsewhere in the specs, we could maybe
nuke this section; the risk is in implementations which might unwisely
trust a Self-Signed TLS Certificate for Onion Services. The above does
appear to be a desirably robust solution, however.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="onion-name-types" title="Onion Name Types">

<t>At the time of writing, “base .onion names” are of two types:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>“old” .onion names, being encodings of truncated SHA-1 hashes</t>
  <t>“new” or “next generation” names, being encodings of X25519 keys and metadata</t>
</list></t>

<t>This standard SHALL NOT prohibit generation of Self-Signed TLS
Certificates for Onion Services for either of these, nor for future,
types of .onion name.</t>

<t>Clients SHOULD implement fine-grained checks to distingush, and to
eventually deprecate, legacy types of .onion name.</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>

&RFC1034;
&RFC1123;
&RFC2119;
&RFC5280;
&RFC7686;


    </references>




  </back>
</rfc>

